前情提要
有一个人名叫德纳迪埃  他救了我的命
A man called Thenardier saved my life.
如果你今后遇见他  尽你所能款待他
If you meet him, do the best you can.
我们现在需要的只是点燃炸药桶的火花
All we need now is a spark to set off the powder keg,
然后全巴黎都会陷入火海
and all Paris could go up in flames!
我们要让城市失控
We must make this city ungovernable!
誓死守卫我们的街垒
And defend this barricade to the death!
我要你们找到那个人  逮捕他
I want that man found, arrested
把他移送法办
and brought to justice.
他在哪里
Where is he?!
-谁  -冉·阿让
- Who? - Jean Valjean.
我们去一个秘密住所
We're moving to a secret address.
那别人怎么找我们
But how would anyone know how to find us?
你想有人来找你吗
Is there someone you wish to be found by?
我亲爱的马吕斯  今晚请过来  或者捎个信
My beloved Marius, please come or send word tonight.
我有封信要给你
I got a letter for you.
放开我
Let me go!
我不能让你出去  巴黎到处都在打仗
I can't let you go! There's fighting all over Paris!
我恨你
I hate you!
她的心已经飞走了
In her heart, she's gone.
七号的信
Got a letter for number seven.
亲爱的  现在我和朋友们在街垒上
My darling, I am now on the barricades with my friends...
若我死了  我爱你至死不渝
If I die, I die loving you.
立正
Attention!
悲惨世界
第一季  第六集  [剧终]
你看到什么了
So, what did you see?
都结束了  同志
It's all over, comrade.
成百名士兵正准备进攻
Hundreds of soldiers are getting ready to attack.
多数街垒都被摧毁了
And most of the barricades have been destroyed.
你没事吧
Are you all right?
我
Me?
再好不过了
Never better.
所有人都出去  你们都得听听
Everybody outside, now. You need to hear this.
马吕斯  古费拉克
Marius. Courfeyrac.
醒醒
Wake up!
天啊
For God's sake!
市民们
Citizens!
最后的时刻到来了
This...is the endgame.
留下来继续战斗就等于选择死亡
Every man and woman who stays here and fights today will die.
历史会铭记我们
History will remember us
总有一天人民会胜利
and one day the people will prevail.
但现在  全巴黎的军队都出动了
But, for now, the whole Paris army is out
一小时之内我们就会交锋
and within an hour they will be upon us.
你们没有希望了
You have nothing to expect.
没有一点希望
Nothing to hope for.
那就上吧
So be it!
我们把街垒筑得更高些  战斗到最后一人
Let's raise the barrier higher, and fight till the last man!
朋友们  想想吧
Friends, consider!
你们有妻子丈夫  儿子女儿
Some of you have wives, husbands, sons, daughters.
想想他们
Think of them.
英勇牺牲对他们无益
A heroic death will do nothing for them.
你被杀  他们就会挨饿
You get yourself killed, they starve.
甚至更惨
Or worse.
你们活下来才更勇敢  为了你们的家人
For you, it is a braver thing to live, for your family's sake!
安灼拉说得对
Enjolras is right!
你们活下去  改日再战  这没什么可丢脸的
There's no shame on you living to fight another day.
所有已婚的人  有家要养的人  站出来
Every married man and woman, every breadwinner, come forward,
跟我们握手告别
shake our hands, and leave!
我命令你们
I command you!
我恳求你们
I entreat you!
同志
Comrade.
好好活下去  同志
Live well, comrade.
你要创造一个更美好的世界
You'll be building a better world.
一个我们看不到的世界
A world we won't be seeing.
你确定你要留在这吗
Are you quite sure you want to be here?
确定
Yes.
爸爸
Papa?
你好  小姐
Bonjour, mademoiselle.
你见到我爸爸了吗
Have you seen Papa?
没有
No.
小姐  回来  小姐  回来
Mademoiselle, come back! Mademoiselle, come back!
准备战斗
Prepare yourselves.
小姐  小姐
Mademoiselle! Mademoiselle!
-回去  回去  -马吕斯
- Get back! Get back! - Marius!
-别上街  -马吕斯
- Get back off the street! - Marius!
马吕斯
Marius!
-快看  -就位
- Look! - Positions!
准备战斗
Prepare yourselves!
大家准备好
Brace yourselves!
大炮
Cannon fire!
开炮
Fire!
趴下
Get down!
Stay down!
上  上
Move! Move!
来  来
Allez! Allez!
撤退
Fall back!
他们撤退了
They're falling back!
公民  共和国感谢你
Citizen, the Republic thanks you.
我不认识你  也不知道你为什么来这里
I don't know who you are, or why you are here,
但是我很高兴你来加入我们
but I'm glad to have you with us.
同志们
Comrades!
这是一个严峻的历史时刻...
This is a grim moment in our history...
.. 但也是光辉的一刻
..but a glorious one!
我们的牺牲将有助于建设一个更好的世界
Our sacrifice is going to help build a better world.
这个街垒不仅仅是用
This barricade is made of more than
石块和床架建成的
just cobblestones and bedsteads.
它是由同胞们的希望
It is made of hopes,
理想
of ideals,
和爱建成的
of love of our fellow men.
我们是为这世上所有不幸的人而战
We fight for the wretched of the Earth!
即便我们会死
And if we go to our deaths,
我们也是慷慨赴义
we go to our deaths with joy!
共和国万岁
Long live the Republic!
革命万岁
Vive la revolution!
马吕斯  马吕斯
Marius! Marius.
我们争取了一些时间
We've bought ourselves some time.
问题是我们快没有子弹了
The trouble is, we're running out of bullets.
交给我吧
Leave that to me.
加夫罗什  加夫罗什
Gavroche! Gavroche!
快回来
Come back here!
加夫罗什  回来
Gavroche, come back!
加夫罗什
Gavroche!
你会让自己送命的
You'll get yourself killed.
这些尸体
The corpses!
加夫罗什
Gavroche!
运气不好  再来呀
Bad luck, try again.
加夫罗什
Gavroche!
好枪法...
Good shot...
别犯傻
Don't be a fool!
快点  马吕斯
Quickly, Marius!
来吧...
Come on...
我们有子弹了
We got them.
愿赌服输...
It was good sport...
..  是不是
..wasn't it?
可怜的小东西
Poor little squirt.
他说什么
What did he say?
他说...
He said...
他说愿赌服输
He said it was good sport.
还有...
And...
安灼拉
Enjolras!
把他弄屋里  快
Get him inside, quickly.
-把他扶起来  -包扎一下伤口
- Get him up. - Dress his wound.
来吧  来吧
Come here. Come on.
马吕斯  马吕斯
Marius. Marius!
睁开眼睛
Open your eyes.
这是我们最后的阵地
This is our last refuge.
他们攻占了街垒以后
When they take the barricade,
还活着人的可以在这继续战斗
those left alive can fight on here.
他怎么办
What about him?
那个奸细警察
The police spy?
最后一个活着的人可以朝他头上开一枪
The last man alive can put a bullet in his head.
我能来执行这光荣的使命吗  行行好
May I claim that honour? As a favour?
我觉得没问题
I don't see why not.
他归你了
He's yours.
开枪
Fire!
快  同志们  走
Come on, comrades. Go.
本该如此
Just so.
那就来吧
Go on, then.
来报仇吧
Take your revenge.
对啊
Oh, yeah.
用刀子才更像你的风格
A blade would be more your style.
闭上嘴
Shut your mouth.
行了
There.
你自由了  快走吧
You're free. Now go.
什么意思
What is this?
如果我能活下来  虽说希望不大...
If I come through this alive, which isn't very likely...
.. 你可以来武人街抓我
..you can find me at Rue de l'Homme-Arme.
七号
Number seven.
-我不会拒捕的  -你在做什么
- I shan't resist arrest. - What are you doing?
我没理由要你的命  趁我改主意之前赶紧走
I've no reason to take your life. Now go, before I change my mind.
你不想把握住杀我的机会吗
What, you're not going to take your opportunity?
你想死吗
Do you wish to die?
这总比放了我要说得通
It would make a hell of a lot more sense than this.
好吧  那你只能自己去寻死了  现在赶紧走
Yeah, well, you'll have to arrange it yourself. Now go. Go.
快走
Just go!
回来  回来
Get back! Get back!
回来
Get back!
古费拉克
Courfeyrac!
快  快
Come on, come on
这会载入史册  这会载入史册
This is history. This is history.
拜托
Come on!
什么情况
What the hell's going on?
去找你自己的酒鬼
Find your own boozer!
伙计 那真疼
Bugger, that hurt!
他是带头的
He's the leader.
-朝他站的地方开枪  -等等
- Shoot him where he stands. - Wait a minute!
我也是
Me too.
共和国万岁
Long live the Republic.
排好队  伙计们
Line up, lads.
你们有权选择蒙上眼睛
You're entitled to be blindfolded.
-你们想要眼罩吗  -去你妈的眼罩
- Do you want the blindfold? - I piss on your blindfold.
瞄准
Take aim.
开火
Fire!
这个人是罪犯  骗子和小偷
This man is a criminal, a liar and a thief.
人间的渣滓
The scum of the Earth!
你是个肮脏的小偷
You're a dirty thief!
全是他的错
It's all his fault.
你看到这个恶魔了吗  恶魔
You see this monster? Monster!
全是他的错  罪犯  骗子  小偷
It's all his fault. ..Criminal, liar and a thief...
肮脏的小偷  恶魔
Dirty thief! Monster!
人间的渣滓
Scum of the Earth!
肮脏的小偷  人间的渣滓
Dirty thief! Scum of the Earth!
我恨你  恶魔
I hate you! Monster!
请原谅我
Forgive me.
Forgive me!
-站住  -退下
- Hold it there! - Get back.
你回来了  长官
You're back, sir.
你没事吧
You all right?
如你所见  里韦特
As you see, Rivette.
好吧
Well, er...
有报告称你被叛军抓住了
..There was a report that you'd been captured by the rebels.
然而我在这
Yet here I am.
你见到他了吗  你追的那个人  冉阿让
Did you see him? The one you're after, that man Valjean?
是的  我见到他了
Yes, I saw him.
发生什么了  他被抓起来了吗
What happened? Is he in custody?
不
No.
他逃走了
He got away?
他放我走了
He allowed me to get away.
看来你也有心软的时候  长官
Must have a soft spot for you, sir.
你在嘲笑我吗
Are you mocking me?
没有  长官
No, sir.
那些叛军都被杀了
You know they were all killed, the rebels.
-他的尸体找到了吗  -不知道  长官
- Was his body found with the others? - Don't know, sir.
那他依然在逃
Then he's still at large.
还有另一个人  德纳迪埃
And the other fella, Thenardier,
有人看到他在河边
he's been sighted down by the river.
由于暴乱  这些人渣都冒出来了
These riots seem to have brought all the scum to the surface.
我刚刚正打算去那边
I was just on my way down there.
你愿意一起来吗  长官
Do you wish to come, sir?
我们最精锐的人手已经准备好了  长官
Got some of our best men standing by, sir.
我觉得有机会
I think there's a chance
-能把他们一锅端  -很好
- we might net the whole gang of them. - Good.
做得好  里韦特
Well done, Rivette.
请允许我  长官
Just permit me, sir...
把手拿开
Take your hands off me.
请原谅我  长官
Forgive me, sir.
请原谅
Beg your pardon.
没事了
It's all right...
All right.
你没事了
You're all right.
坚持住  撑住
Stay alive. Stay alive!
天哪
Stay... Oh, God...
马吕斯·彭眉胥
Marius Pontmercy.
原来是你
So that's who you are.
如果我死了  把我的遗体带给我的祖父
If I die, take my body to my grandfather.
吉诺曼先生
Monsieur Gillenormand,
受难修女街六号
number six, Rue des Filles-du-Calvaire...
你真是个混蛋
Oh, you...you're really in the shit, aren't you, eh?
混蛋
The shit!
请原谅  天呐  这味道
Forgive me. Ooh! The smell of you, eh?
你不属于这里吧
You're really not at home here, are you?
你不了解这里的路  你不属于这里
You don't know your way around, it's not your milieu.
你想怎样
What do you want?
我就想知道你现在要怎么办
Oh, I'm just wondering about what you're going to do now.
你要如何走出去
How you're going to get out there.
你不知道  对吧
You don't know, do you?
你被困住了
You're stuck.
真尴尬
Ah, shame.
我们以前也算不上朋友  是吧
We've not been friends in the past, have we?
但我现在可以帮你
But I could help you now.
你把你在那个人口袋里找到的分我一半
You give me half of what you've found in that man's pockets,
我就帮你打开门
and I'll open up the gate for you.
你为什么会觉得
What makes you think...
他口袋里有东西
..He had anything in his pockets?
要不是他有值得拥有的东西
Well, you wouldn't have killed him
你也不会杀了他  对吧
unless he had something worth having, now, would you?
五五分  怎么样
What do you say, 50/50?
好
All right.
你要打开这扇门吗
Are you going to get this gate open?
不用担心
Ah, no need to worry about that.
这里可是我的地盘
This is my territory down here, yeah?
现在先看看你有什么
Now let's see what you've got.
来啊  我们来交易
Come on. Let's trade.
在这  好极了
There. Ye-e-e-es!
就这些吗
Is that all?
就为这么点东西割断一个人的喉咙
Not much for slitting a man's throat.
都在这了
That's all.
十法郎  你确定吗  不好意思
Ten francs? Are you sure? With your permission...
手伸出来  伸出来
Arms out. Arms out!
这世道也抢不到多少了
Hardly worth it these days, is it, eh?
成王败寇
The robbery game.
谁都没什么钱
No-one's got nothing no more.
好吧  先生  我带你出去  带上你的朋友
All right, mister, I'll let you out. Take your friend with you.
要是你想丢下他
Find a rope,
就找根绳子
tie it around a big stone...
把他绑在一块大石头上
...when you dump him.
你不希望他再冒出来吧
You don't want him bobbing up.
来吧
Come on!
走啊  走吧
Go on. Go on!
喂
Oi.
Oi!
你毁了我的生活
You ruined my life.
我曾受人尊敬  也曾富有过
I was a respected man. I had money.
现在我像老鼠一样生活在黑暗中
Now I live like a rat in the shitty darkness!
是他
It's him.
是冉·阿让  沙威探长
It's Jean Valjean. Inspector Javert,
您现在就可以逮捕我
you can take me now,
但请帮我个忙
but grant me one favour.
帮我把这个人带回家见他的祖父
Help me take this man home to his grandfather.
他是谁
Who is he?
他叫马吕斯·彭眉胥
His name's Marius Pontmercy.
他受伤了
He's wounded.
-他看起来死了  -不  还没有
- He looks dead. - No, not yet.
还没有
Not yet.
您能帮我吗
Will you help me?
拜托
Please?
吉诺曼先生
Monsieur Gillenormand!
开门  警察  开门
Open up. Police! Open up!
告诉你家主人我们带回来了他孙子的尸体
Tell your master we've brought his grandson's body home.
您说他孙子
His grandson, you say?
我的天  是马吕斯先生
Oh, my God, it's Monsieur Marius.
轻点  小心
Gently! Careful.
是马吕斯先生
It's Monsieur Marius!
轻点  轻点  小心
Gently, gently. Careful.
谢谢  先生
Merci, monsieur.
马吕斯先生  他们对你做了什么
Monsieur Marius, what have they done to you?
没必要告诉我  他死了  他死了
Ahhhh, no need to tell me... He's dead! He's dead!
他在街垒上被杀  只是为了忤逆我
He's got himself killed on the barricades, just to defy me.
他很清楚我在等他
He knew very well I was waiting for him!
你  你非得这么做吗
You...you had to do it, didn't you,
伤一个老人的心
you had to break an old man's heart...
等等  先生  我能感觉到脉搏
Wait! Monsieur! I can feel a pulse.
上帝保佑他会活下来
Pray God he'll live!
中士  中士  快  把他带上楼
Serge! Serge! Quickly, get him upstairs.
过来  过来  快  快
Come on! Come on! Quickly! Quickly.
快点
Hurry.
再帮我一个忙
One more favour.
让我回趟家
Let me go home.
只要几分钟就好
Just for a few minutes.
然后我便听凭你处置
Then you can do with me what you want.
准许
Granted.
那个年轻人
That young man.
他是
Is he a...
你很特别的朋友吗
particular friend of yours?
他是你珍视的人吗
Would you say he's...dear to you?
恰恰相反
Quite the contrary.
如果他活着  他打算
If he lives, he intends to...
抢走我全部的幸福
rob me of...all my happiness.
然而你却...
And yet you...
你疯了吗
Are you insane?
不  我没有
No, I don't think so.
你呢
Are you?
进去吧
Go in.
我在这里等你
I'll wait for you here.
你相信我吗
You trust me?
进去吧
Go in.
原谅我
Forgive me.
现在你能找到他了
Now you can find him.
沙威
Javert?
Javert?!
沙威
长官
Yes, sir?
我为警务系统的更高效运转
I've been making some recommendations
提了一些建议
for the more efficient running of the service.
我委托你一个任务
I entrust you with the task of bringing them
将这些建议呈给长官们
to the attention of the commissioners.
没问题  长官
Very good, sir.
一切都好吗
All well?
不
No.
里韦特
Rivette...
一切都不好
All is not well.
囚犯阿让
Prisoner Valjean.
他不再是囚犯了
He's no longer a prisoner.
我...
I, er...
我放他自由了
I let him go free.
我能问问原因吗  长官
May I ask why, sir?
我不知道
I don't know.
一种仁慈之举吗
As an act of clemency?
是疯狂之举
An act of madness.
那个人
That man...
那家伙
That man!
我此生深信不疑的一切
Everything I've ever believed to be true.
所有我毕生遵循的原则...
Everything I lived my life by...
而他
And he...
他...
He...
不重要了
No matter.
当然  我将辞去我的职务
I shall, of course, be resigning my commission.
真的吗  长官  一个错误
Really, sir, one mistake...
就算真的是错误  为一个错误
If it is indeed a mistake, one mistake against...
-而辞职...  -经历了这种事  我怎么继续
- a long career... - How can I continue? After this?
我让我自己和警局
I have brought myself and the police service
蒙受耻辱和污名
into disgrace and disrepute.
我需要新鲜空气
I need some fresh air.
我要出去走走
I'm going for a walk.
记得把这些建议
Remember to bring those notes
呈给警务总监
to the attention of the Prefect of Police.
晚安  里韦特
Goodnight, Rivette.
总监先生  我请求您
I beg, Monsieur Le Prefet,
考虑以下几点对改善警务工作的建议
to consider these proposals for improvements to the service.
第一  我们应当终止
First, that we end the practice of prisoners
在从审问归来的囚犯们等待被转移回监狱时
returning from interrogations being made to remove their shoes
强迫他们脱掉鞋子的规程
while they await transport back to the prison.
许多人在回到牢房时都在咳嗽
Many are coughing when they return to their cells.
这将加大医疗开支
This leads to hospital expenses.
第二  在纺织间掉下一根线的囚犯
Second, a prisoner who drops a thread in the weaving room
将被罚十苏  这是滥用...
loses 10 sous. This is an abuse of...
第三  对于特殊规定...
Third, the special regulation of the...
第四  通常情况下监视...
Fourth, surveillance is generally...
第五  警察们...
Fifth, gendarmes...
返回的囚犯们...
Prisoners coming back from the...
革命万岁
Vive la revolution!
马吕斯
Ssh, Marius...
天啊
Oh, my!
我亲爱的孩子
My dear boy...
我怎么到这来了
How did I end up here?
你是被警察带到这来的
You were carried here by the police.
不是警察
Not the police.
是街垒上的一个人
Somebody else. At the barricade.
我欠他一条命
I owe him my life.
他们都死了吗
Are they all dead?
安灼拉  古费拉克  格朗泰尔  所有朋友
Enjolras, Courfeyrac, Grantaire - all my friends.
好像是的
It...would seem so.
他们都白白牺牲了吗
Was it all for nothing?
他们把你带回了我身边  我最亲爱的孩子
It brought you back to me, my dearest boy.
我想结婚
I want to get married.
你确定吗
Do you indeed?
你听见没  他现在想结婚
Did you hear that? He wants to be married now!
都安排好了
All arranged.
什么意思
What do you mean?
就这个意思  你应该跟你的心上人在一起
What I say. You shall have your little sweetheart.
我调查了一下  发现她个百年难见的好姑娘
I've done some investigating, and I find she's a jewel.
而且她喜欢你  所以不用多说了
And she adores you. So, no more to be said.
珂赛特同意了
Cosette agreed.
爱情同意了
Love agreed.
我由衷地感到高兴
I couldn't...be happier.
我心爱的孩子
My beloved child.
父亲
Father...
你听见没  "父亲"
Did you hear that? "Father"!
他还是爱我的
Well, he loves me after all.
现在他得到心爱的姑娘了
Now he's getting the girl he wants!
为什么不呢
Well, why not?
-请进  先生  -马吕斯
- Ah, come in, monsieur. - Marius!
欢迎
You're very welcome.
-珂赛特  -请坐
- Cosette... - Please, please, take a seat.
谢谢
Thank you.
你怎么了
What happened to you?
这不重要
It doesn't matter.
一个不认识的人把我带回了你身边
Someone, I don't know who, brought me back to you.
你真走运  孩子  要是我年轻个15岁
You're very lucky, my boy. If I were 15 years younger,
我们就要拔剑决斗决定谁能娶她了
we'd be drawing swords to see which of us would have her!
真的吗  父亲
Really, Father!
怎么了  我不能也爱上她吗
What's the matter? Can't I be in love with her too?
很正常
It's only natural.
开玩笑的  小姐  他属于你了
I'm joking, Mademoiselle. He's all yours.
你有了一位称职的英俊丈夫了
You have a handsome husband worth his salt.
不要担心钱的问题
No matter about money.
你们的外祖父会照顾你们俩
Your grandpapa will take care of the pair of you.
不  我女儿有嫁妆的
No, my daughter has...has a dowry.
六十五万法郎
650,000 francs.
-六十五万法郎  -都在这了
- 650,000 francs?! - It's all there.
你这个幸运儿
Well, you lucky devil!
你的小宝贝还是个大富翁
Your little dove turns out to be a millionairess!
他们不在乎钱  先生  他们只在乎彼此
They don't care, monsieur. The only care about each other.
年轻人都这样
Ah, what it is to be young!
那我先告辞了  先生
Well, I'll...take my leave, monsieur.
不  不  不  我不同意
No, no, no. I won't hear of it.
现在我们是幸福的一家人了
We're all one happy family now.
-留下来吃晚餐吧  -不了  先生  谢谢
- Stay for dinner. - No, monsieur, thank you.
但还是请你允许我先告辞
But with your permission, I'll take my leave.
再见  珂赛特  你就在这吧
I'll see you later, Cosette. No need for you to come now.
好的  爸爸  再见
Very well, Papa. I'll see you later.
谢谢你
Thank you.
有什么需要帮忙的吗  先生
What can I do for you, monsieur?
恐怕  我得坐下
I'm afraid I... I have to sit down.
我有事要告诉你
I have something to tell you.
我有前科
I am an ex-convict.
二十年前坐过牢
20 years in the prison hulks.
逃狱了  又被抓了回去
Escaped, recaptured.
又逃狱了  现在我正在被通缉
Escaped again. And presently I'm a wanted man.
我是个贼
I'm a thief.
我偷了一位主教的东西  迪涅主教
I stole from a bishop, the Bishop of Digne.
我还抢过一个小孩的东西
I even robbed a child.
你是珂赛特的父亲
You - Cosette's father!
不  我不是她的父亲
No, I'm not her father.
她是个孤儿
She was an orphan.
是我找到了她
I found her.
我是个无名之辈  法沃罗勒的农民
I am no-one. I'm a peasant from Faverolles.
我犯下的第一个罪行是偷了一块面包
My first crime was to steal a loaf of bread.
知道了吗  我...
Do you see? I'm...
我是个苦役犯
I'm a common criminal.
我就知道你有问题
I knew there was something.
我记得  在客栈
I remember, at the tavern.
你朝那个警察开了枪
You shot that police officer.
你来街垒就是为了杀他  是吗
Is that why you came to the barricade, to kill him?
那如果我说我来街垒
What if I told you I came to the barricades
心里是抱有杀你的想法呢
with half a mind to kill you?
没错  这就是你的处境
Yes, you see, that's what you're dealing with.
我的天哪
For God's sake.
我如今该怎么看你
What am I to think of you now?
你随便怎么看我都行
Think of me as you wish.
我只想让你知道真相
I wanted you to know the truth
然后我可以平静地离开你们
so that I could take my leave of her, and you, in peace.
我不属于任何人的家庭  先生
I don't belong in the family of men, monsieur.
我是外人
I'm on the outside.
可怜的珂赛特  等她发现你走了
Poor Cosette! When she finds out...
别  我求求你  先生  别告诉她
No, I beg you, monsieur, I beg you. Spare her that.
你不能要求我不告诉她
You can't ask me to keep this from her!
先生
Monsieur...
有天她和我在一起的时候
..One day, when she was with me...
她看见一群犯人经过
..She saw the chain gang go by.
她忍不住开始想
And she couldn't bear to think...
那种像我一样的坏人
..That such wicked men existed.
竟然依然存在
Men like me.
如果你保守了这个秘密
If you keep my secret, I promise,
我保证在婚礼结束之后就永远在你们的生活里消失
that after the wedding I shall get out of your lives forever.
好吧
Agreed.
谢谢你  先生
Thank you, monsieur.
日安  彭眉胥男爵
Good day, Baron Pontmercy.
祝你一生幸福
I wish you a happy life.
她真漂亮啊
Ah, elle est jolie!
-爸爸  -怎么了亲爱的
- Papa? - Yes, my dear?
你开心吗
Are you happy?
我当然开心  为你感到开心
Course I'm happy. Happy for you.
那你为什么不笑呢
Then why aren't you smiling?
我会想念你  所以笑不出来
I'm just... I'm going to miss you. That's all.
别这样想  爸爸
Don't be silly, Papa.
蜜月很快就结束了
The honeymoon will be over before we know it,
我六周后就回来了
and I'll be back in six weeks.
那时候我们又可以一直见面了
And...then we will see each other all of the time.
六周后
-谢谢  我终于到家啦  -辛苦了  伙计们
- Thank you. I'm glad to be home. - Thank you, gentlemen.
我还是觉得我们应该先去看爸爸
I still think we should go and see Papa first.
他肯定想知道我们的蜜月旅程
He'll be wanting to know all about our wedding journey.
-一会儿的吧  来  亲爱的  -尼科莱特
- Maybe later. Come on, darling. - Nicolette!
小姐
Madame!
先生
Monsieur!
-谢谢先生  -欢迎回家
- Merci, monsieur. - Oh, welcome home!
你有个来访者
Ah. There's a visitor to see you.
他说事情非常重要
Very important, the gentleman said.
-我让他在客厅等候  -好的
- I put him in the drawing-room. - Very well.
你好  男爵先生
Bonjour, Monsieur Le Baron.
你来这里干什么
What are you doing here?
先生  我是来
Monsieur, I just thought I'd congratulate you
祝您新婚快乐的
on your wedding day.
小姐  您看起来美极了
And, Madame, you look so beautiful.
但我还记得我们刚在蒙费梅伊见到你的时候
But I remember when you were a skinny little guttersnipe
你还是个瘦得皮包骨的流浪儿
we picked up at Montfermeil.
德纳迪埃
Thenardier.
对  就是我
That's me.
马吕斯  这个人很坏
Marius, this man is evil.
小时候是我爸爸把我从他手里救下来的
My father saved me from him when I was a little girl.
你爸爸
Your father...
让我来给你讲讲你的爸爸
Let me tell you something about your father.
-珂赛特  上楼去  我来处理  -你想要什么
- Cosette, go upstairs, I'll deal with this. - What do you want here?
我得到一点消息
I've got some information
听完可以让你头发都竖起来
for you that'll make your hair stand on end.
-什么消息  -我想要一点回报
- What information? - I want a little something in exchange.
我想去新大陆那边的拉贺拉做个小生意
I want to set up a business. In La Jolla. The New World.
那里有钱可赚  有奴隶可交易
There's money to be made there, slaves to trade.
-你的消息是什么  -珂赛特
- And your information is? - Cosette.
那个老男人  你所谓的爸爸
That old fella, your so-called father,
是个飞贼兼刺客
is a thief and an assassin.
如果我是你  我不会容许他在这个家里  不安全
I wouldn't have him in the house if I was you. Not safe.
我都知道
I know all this.
他自己告诉我的
He told me so himself.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
他都杀过谁
Who did he kill, then?
他杀了那个沙威督察
He killed the police spy, Javert.
对不起  珂赛特
I'm sorry, Cosette.
那不是真的
Well, I... It's not true.
你怎么会相信这样的事
How could you believe such a thing?
她说得对  因为他没死
She's right. Cos he didn't.
沙威自杀的
Javert did himself in.
我亲眼看到的  从桥上跳下去死的
I saw it with my own eyes. Threw himself off a bridge, he did.
那老家伙杀了一个年轻的小伙子
Nah, the one that the old fella killed was a young chap.
我在他杀死他以后在下水道里见到了他
I met him in the sewers just after he'd done it.
他本来准备把那个小伙子扔进河里
He was going to dump the young chap in the river.
那个小伙子长什么样
What did he look like, this young chap?
跟他个头差不多  我不知道  你想说什么
About his size. I don't know. What are you saying?
你全弄错了  你这个老蠢货
You've got it all wrong, you old fool.
他救了你的命
He was saving your life!
肯定是他把你带回家的
He must have been the man that carried you home.
他救了我的命
He saved my life.
他救了你的命
He saved your life.
那我呢
What about me?!
你
You?
你本来是想抹黑一个人
You came here to ruin a man...
却无心让他变得无比光辉
..And you crowned him with glory.
你就是个骗子  还很愚蠢
You're a liar, and a stupid one at that.
你就是个骗子  你是杀人犯
And you're the thief, you're the murderer.
我看到你在那个肮脏的贫民窟做的事了
I saw what you did in that squalid slum.
我可以上你下半辈子都在监狱里度过
I could have you chained up for the rest of your life.
在我改变主意之前  别想重见天日
Now get out before I change my mind.
等等
Wait.
带上这个
Take this with you.
一千法郎
1,000 francs.
我知道你在滑铁卢战争中救了我父亲
I understand you saved my father's life at Waterloo.
那个上校
The Colonel...
彭眉胥男爵
..Baron Pontmercy.
男爵先生和夫人
Monsieur and Madame Pontmercy, er...
曾经还是善有善报的
..Once in a lifetime, virtue is rewarded, eh?
感激不尽
My eternal gratitude.
爸爸  爸爸
Papa? Papa!
珂赛特
Cosette?
他离开了
He's gone away.
那些烛台
The candlesticks -
都不见了
they're gone.
很抱歉我一直瞒着你  珂赛特
I'm sorry I kept the truth from you, Cosette.
我向你父亲保证过
I made a promise to your father.
马吕斯
Marius...
我觉得我知道他可能在哪里
..I think I know where he might be.
爸爸
Papa?
Papa.
是你们
It's you.
你们来了
You've come?
你带走了烛台
You took the candlesticks.
我就觉得我们也许能来迪涅找到你
I thought we might find you in Digne.
你救了我的命  却从来没有告诉过我
You saved my life, and never told me.
先生
Oh, monsieur...
我以为我以后再也见不到她了
I thought I'd never see her again.
珂赛特
Cosette.
爸爸
Oh, Papa.
你不知道我不值得你的爱吗
Didn't you know, I'm not worthy of your love?
-我不值得任何人的爱  -别这么说
- I'm not worthy of anybody's love. - Don't speak like that.
我都知道了
I know everything.
你为什么要离开躲起来
Why did you run away and hide?
爸爸  爸爸
Oh... Oh, Papa! Papa...
爸爸  你的手  好冷
Papa, your hands, they're so cold.
因为我快要死了
That's because I'm going to die soon.
不
No.
不  你没有
No, you're not.
你不会的  因为
You won't, because...
因为我不会让你死的
Because I won't let you.
你要和我们一起回家
You're coming home with us.
我要绑架你
I'm going to kidnap you.
你真的爱我吗
Do you really love me?
爸爸  爸爸
Oh, Papa. Papa.
你还在吗
Are you still there?
是的  爸爸
Yes, Papa.
我有事情...要告诉你
I had...things to tell you.
算了
Never mind.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
彼此相爱
Love each other.
先生
Monsieur!
-先生  -不
- Monsieur! - No.
先生
Monsieur!